Finding Aid for the Allen Tate Papers Correspondence and Manuscripts Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Allen tate Papers Correspondence and Manuscripts Collection
1923-1974
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0431
.21 linear_feet
Biographical Note
John Orley Allen Tate was born near Winchester, Kentucky November 19, 1899. He graduated from Vanderbilt University Magna Cum Laude, Phi Beta Kappa in 1922. During this time at Vanderbilt he became one of the Fugitive poets who published their magazine The Fugitive during the years 1922-1925. Later he contributed an essay to the Agrarian manifesto I’ll Take My Stand (1930) and in 1936 he was co-editor with Herbert Agar of Who Owns America? He published poetry throughout his long career and was an accomplished man of letters writing one novel The Fathers (1938), criticism, and biographies.Tate was also the editor at The Sewanee Review from 1944-46. He received many awards for his poetry including the Bollingen Prize in 1956 and held the Chair of Poetry at the Library of Congress in 1943-44.
Allen Tate was also a teacher with appointments at among others the Women’s College of the University of North Carolina, Princeton, New York University, and the University of Minnesota where he taught from 1951 until his retirement in 1968.
He was married twice to the writer Caroline Gordon from 1924 to 1959. They had a daughter Nancy born in 1924. After his divorce from Caroline Gordon in 1959 he married poet Isabella Gardner. And after his divorce from Gardner in 1966 he married his former student at Minnesota Helen Heinz. They had three sons, one of whom died in an accident in infancy.
Tate lived in many places including England and France (on a Guggenheim Fellowship), New York, Minnesota, Sewanee, and at his farm Benfolly near Clarksville, Tennessee. He had lifelong friendships with writers Robert Penn Warren, Donald Davidson, Andrew Lytle, Hart Crane, Ernest Hemingway, Ford Madox Ford, John Peale Bishop.
Allen Tate died in Nashville, Tennessee in February 1979. His papers are at the Firestone Library at Princeton University.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection (.21 linear feet) includes personal correspondence between Allen Tate and family members Benjamin E. Tate, Sr., Benjamin E. Tate, Jr. (Chuck), and Louise Fleishman Tate. There are also letters to J. Edgar Simmons and others, and incoming letters from Mark Van Doren, William S. Knickerbocker, and others making a total of 39 letters. The collection also includes the Chronology and Resume of Allen Tate, typescripts of two poems and several articles by Tate.
- Outgoing Correspondence—Miscellaneous (4 letters), 1931, 1937, 1960, undated (Folder 1, Box 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence Allen Tate to J.Edgar Simmons (6 letters), 1949-1964 (Folder 2, Box 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence Allen Tate to Benjamin E.Tate, Sr. (11 letters), 1932-1961 (Folder 3, Box 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence Allen Tate to Benjamin E. Tate, Jr. (Chuck) (9 letters), 1968-1974 (Folder 4, Box 1)
- Outgoing Correspondence Allen Tate to Louise Fleishman Tate and related documents (4 letters), 1974 (Folder 5, Box 1)
- Incoming Correspondence—Miscellaneous (5 letters), 1926-27 (Folder 6, Box 1)
- Personal and Biographical, Chronology of Tate’s Life 1899-1966; Resume 1974 (Folder 7, Box 1)
- Writings—Poem (Folder 8, Box 1)
- “The Meditteranean” typescript, signed (Folder 8, Box 1)
- Writings—Poem (Folder 9, Box 1)
- “Shadow and Shade” typescript, signed (Folder 9, Box 1)
- Writings—Letter to the Editor (Folder 10, Box 1)
- The Literary Review/Re: John Crowe Ransom and The Waste Land, August 4, 1923 (Folder 10, Box 1)
- Writings—Article (Folder 11, Box 1)
- “Mere Literature and the Lost Traveller” (Folder 11, Box 1)
- (4th Annual Williamson Memorial Lecture), Reprint, July 17, 1969 (Folder 11, Box 1)
- Writings—Article (Folder 12, Box 1)
- “Mere Literature and the Lost Traveller” (Folder 12, Box 1)
- Photocopy of typescript with note (Folder 12, Box 1)
- Writings—Article (Folder 13, Box 1)
- “Some Influences of Baudelaire” in Bulletin Baudelairien, Le 31 Aout 1969 (Folder 13, Box 1)
- With typescript, program, and letter from W.T. Bandy (Folder 13, Box 1)
- Writings—Incomplete typescript (Folder 14, Box 1)
- Sixty American Poets, A-K (Folder 14, Box 1)
- Original Register; Description of Series; Chronology, Listing of Correspondence by Tate (Folder 15, Box 1)